<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving
and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">

<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">

<front>


<article-meta>


<title-group>
<article-title>Remote Sensing Methods for Identifying Ephemeral Water
Bodies Across Arizona</article-title>
</title-group>

<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0009-0006-0181-3099</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Zalesky</surname>
<given-names>Travis</given-names>
</name>
<string-name>Travis Zalesky</string-name>

<email>travisz@arizona.edu</email>
<role vocab="https://credit.niso.org" vocab-term="investigation" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/">Investigation</role>
<role vocab="https://credit.niso.org" vocab-term="project
administration" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/project-administration/">Project
administration</role>
<role vocab="https://credit.niso.org" vocab-term="software" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/software/">Software</role>
<role vocab="https://credit.niso.org" vocab-term="visualization" vocab-term-identifier="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/visualization/">Visualization</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">a</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor-1">&#x002A;</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff-1">
<institution-wrap>
<institution>University of Arizona</institution>
</institution-wrap>







</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor-1">travisz@arizona.edu</corresp>
</author-notes>









<history></history>


<abstract>
<p>A variety of remote sensing methods are investigated for their
ability to detect ephemeral water bodies across the state of Arizona.
The strengths and weaknesses of each are discussed.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
<kwd>ephemeral (transient) water</kwd>
<kwd>flood</kwd>
<kwd>LandSat</kwd>
<kwd>MODIS</kwd>
<kwd>playa</kwd>
<kwd>remote sensing</kwd>
<kwd>satellite data</kwd>
<kwd>sheet flow</kwd>
<kwd>synthetic aperture radar (SAR)</kwd>
</kwd-group>




</article-meta>

</front>

<body>
<sec id="introduction">
  <title>1 Introduction</title>
  <p>As part of the Arizona Tri-University Recharge (ATUR) project,
  multiple methods for identifying and quantifying ephemeral water
  bodies across the state of Arizona (AZ) have been investigated. For
  reasons that will be discussed, accurate identification of ephemeral,
  or temporary, water bodies is a challenge, and efforts to-date have
  shown limited success. Methods, results, and challenges are discussed,
  and potential paths forward shall be explored.</p>
  <p>Ephemeral water bodies are common features in the arid American
  southwest. Typically very shallow, these water bodies range in size
  from a few cm rock pools to sheet flow associated with flash floods,
  and playas up to several km in diameter
  (<xref alt="Crawford, 1981" rid="ref-Clifford_Crawford" ref-type="bibr">Crawford,
  1981</xref>;
  <xref alt="Whitford &amp; Duval, 2020" rid="ref-Whitford_Duval_2020" ref-type="bibr">Whitford
  &amp; Duval, 2020</xref>). While playas and intermittent streams are
  well mapped across AZ, there is no consensus on the volume of water
  which flows through these systems. More to the point, there is no
  widely accepted estimate of the volume of water which either
  evaporates or recharges from these internally draining basins.</p>
  <p>It is not clear what fraction of water which flows onto a playa is
  evaporated vs. recharged. On the one hand, the nature of playas
  results in the slow accumulation of surface salts and fine sediments
  (clays and silts), which are generally impervious and detrimental to
  infiltration and subsequent recharge
  (<xref alt="Whitford &amp; Duval, 2020" rid="ref-Whitford_Duval_2020" ref-type="bibr">Whitford
  &amp; Duval, 2020</xref>). Additionally, playas may be an oasis for
  drought resistant flora, increasing local evapotranspiration, even
  after shallow surface soil layers have dried out
  (<xref alt="Crawford, 1981" rid="ref-Clifford_Crawford" ref-type="bibr">Crawford,
  1981</xref>). Alternately, these mineral rich surface crusts may be
  prone to expansion when wetted, and are frequently characterized by
  deep cracks which provide avenues for water infiltration below the
  impervious layers
  (<xref alt="Whitford &amp; Duval, 2020" rid="ref-Whitford_Duval_2020" ref-type="bibr">Whitford
  &amp; Duval, 2020</xref>). While the majority of water flowing onto
  most playas will be lost to evaporation, there may be specific playas
  where water loss by infiltration may exceed evaporation
  (<xref alt="Whitford &amp; Duval, 2020" rid="ref-Whitford_Duval_2020" ref-type="bibr">Whitford
  &amp; Duval, 2020</xref>). At least initially, we will assume that all
  water flowing onto playas shall be evaporated, subject to later
  reevaluation and refinement.</p>
  <p>The primary target of this study is to estimate and quantify the
  volume of water flowing into small to medium sized playas, on the
  order of ~500 m to ~10 km in diameter, although identification of
  sheet flow may also be incidental. The general method outlined is to
  use remote sensing technology to identify standing water broadly
  across the study area, across a time series. By identifying standing
  water, and assuming a constant water depth, water volume can be
  estimated. Additionally, an approximation of “continuously wetted”
  days can provide an initial estimate of evaporation rates, and through
  comparison with alternate evapotranspiration estimates, may be useful
  for estimating infiltration rate (e.g. if water loss rate is 2 cm/day
  and the evapotranspiration rate is 1.5 cm/day then the implied
  infiltration rate would be 0.5 cm/day).</p>
  <p>The study area used for method development is primarily Hualapai
  (pronounced “wall-a-pie”) Playa (a.k.a. Red Lake), located in
  northwest AZ, approx. 60 km southeast of Lake Mead
  (<xref alt="Figure 1" rid="fig-PlayaRef">Figure 1</xref>). This
  ephemeral playa is roughly 8 km in diameter, and is one of the largest
  playas in AZ. Furthermore, local landowners surrounding Hualapai Playa
  have expressed sincere interest in our project, creating additional
  public-relations incentives related to this particular playa. Lastly,
  it’s proximity to Lake Mead and Lake Mohave provide a convenient
  region for testing these methods against known areas of permanent
  surface water. Additional playas are investigated as needed.</p>
  <fig id="fig-PlayaRef">
    <caption><p>Figure 1: Hualapai Playa locator map.</p></caption>
    <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="images/Hualapai_Playa_Reference.png" />
  </fig>
  <p>One of the most challenging aspects of developing these methods is
  the lack of quality ground-truth data. Without existing data regarding
  date and duration of standing water within these ephemeral features,
  it is extremely difficult to validate our methods. While reasonable
  assumptions can be made about method accuracy (or inaccuracy as the
  case may be), any method, either those presented herein, or future
  methods not yet considered, will have to be validated using a known
  and well characterized ephemeral water body, ideally within AZ, or
  elsewhere in a similar arid environment.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="methods-results">
  <title>2 Methods &amp; Results</title>
  <sec id="method-1-otsu-thresholding-with-synthetic-aperture-radar">
    <title>2.1 Method 1: Otsu Thresholding with Synthetic Aperture
    Radar</title>
    <p>Otsu thresholding is an unsupervised machine vision technique
    which seeks an optimal threshold for segmenting an image into a
    binary classification based on a simple histogram classification
    (<xref alt="Otsu et al., 1975" rid="ref-otsu1975threshold" ref-type="bibr">Otsu
    et al., 1975</xref>). The method was initially developed in the late
    ’70s, and is widely applicable to a range of computer vision
    classification problems. It assumes a bi-modal histogram
    distribution and determines an optimal thresholding value through
    the integration of the histogram, rather than simply relying on
    local histogram properties “such as valley[s]”
    (<xref alt="Otsu et al., 1975" rid="ref-otsu1975threshold" ref-type="bibr">Otsu
    et al., 1975</xref>). In recent years, Otsu thresholding has been
    combined with Synthetic Aperture Radar (SAR) satellite imagery to
    map surface water, such as flood monitoring in the Mekong Delta
    (<xref alt="Tran et al., 2022" rid="ref-Tran_Menenti_Jia_2022" ref-type="bibr">Tran
    et al., 2022</xref>). The properties of surface water and SAR make
    an ideal pairing for use in Otsu thresholding. The smooth surface
    characteristics of surface water create low SAR back-scatter,
    appearing as very dark pixels (Figures
    <xref alt="2" rid="fig-scatter">2</xref>-<xref alt="3" rid="fig-LakeMead_S1">3</xref>).
    Compared to the surrounding land surface, water typically has a very
    high contrast in SAR imagery, which can be leveraged for Otsu
    thresholding. Additionally, the cloud penetrating characteristics of
    SAR offer unparalleled all-weather monitoring capabilities.</p>
    <fig id="fig-scatter">
      <caption><p>Figure 2: Synthetic Aperture Radar signal return
      strength (i.e. back-scatter) is a function the roughness of the
      ground surface. Credit: Meyer
      (<xref alt="2019" rid="ref-Franz_Meyer_2019" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>),
      Figure 2.8. For educational purposes only.</p></caption>
      <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="images/wavelength_vs_roughness.png" />
    </fig>
    <fig id="fig-LakeMead_S1">
      <caption><p>Figure 3: High resolution Synthetic Aperture Radar
      (SAR) imagery of Lake Mead, obtained from the European Space
      Agency (ESA) Sentinel-1 satellite (1-1-2020). Surface water
      appears dark, and contrasts strongly with the surrounding land
      surface, resulting in a bimodal histogram distribution, ideal for
      use in Otsu thresholding.</p></caption>
      <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="images/LakeMead_S1.png" />
    </fig>
    <p>This method initially seemed like an ideal solution. High
    resolution SAR imagery is freely available from the European Space
    Agency (ESA) Sentinel-1 satellite, with a global coverage from late
    2014 to present, and a 6-day revisit time. Google Earth Engine (GEE)
    code for Otsu thresholding was easily adapted from Markert et al.
    (<xref alt="2023" rid="ref-GEE_A2.3" ref-type="bibr">2023</xref>),
    and preliminary results appeared to be promising. Initial analysis
    appeared to show surface water ponding on Huyalapai Playa in mid-Jan
    2020. These preliminary results were circulated internally, and
    purported to be both evidence of surface water, and proof-of-concept
    for method validation. However, further research and wider
    application of this method revealed two critical flaws.</p>
    <p>Firstly, the method, as applied in GEE, was highly sensitive to
    the size and characteristics of any given playa. For larger playas,
    the method was generally suitable, but required a substantial amount
    of manual parameter optimization to function properly. For small to
    medium sized playas, the method was largely unstable, resulting in
    persistent errors. As a result this method is not particularly
    scalable, and at best could be used for a selection of the states
    largest playas, such as Huyalapai and Willcox Dry Lake (southeast
    AZ).</p>
    <p>More critically, this method is sub-optimal for arid regions, as
    flat sandy surfaces also result in low SAR back-scatter, appearing
    similar or indistinguishable from surface water. The hard-pan
    surface of a dry playa is particularly apt to be misidentified by
    this method, resulting in a high likelihood of false positives. It
    is currently unclear if the preliminary results purporting to have
    identified surface water on Huyalapai Playa in Jan. 2020 are true or
    false positives, as there is no associated ground-truthing data
    against which to compare. Regardless of the truthiness of these
    results it is evident that this method can not be used reliably
    within the study area without widespread and comprehensive testing
    and validation of results. Given the scheduling and budgetary
    constraints of this project widespread survey data collection is not
    feasible, and while further development of this method may be
    warranted (generally), it is not appropriate for our purposes.
    Therefore alternate methods must be explored.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="method-2-normalized-difference-water-index-with-landsat-multispectral-imagery">
    <title>2.2 Method 2: Normalized Difference Water Index with Landsat
    Multispectral Imagery</title>
    <p>Collectively, the 9 Landsat satellites provide the longest
    continuous record of space-based earth observations, from 1973 to
    present. Therefore, it may seem like an obvious candidate for
    monitoring infrequent phenomena, such as surface water ponding on
    playas, which may only happen once every several years (depending on
    the playa). However, Landsat imagery has several disadvantages
    compared to SAR. Firstly, the 30 m resolution of Landsat imagery is
    nine times coarser than the 10 m resolution of Sentinel-1 SAR.
    Second, the revisit time for Landsat satellites is 16-days, more
    than double that of Sentinel-1. By combining data from multiple
    Landsat satellites this effective revisit time may be cut to 8-days,
    but this may not be possible throughout the full time series of
    interest. Additionally, the visible and infrared spectral bands used
    by Landsat sensors are not capable of penetrating clouds, and while
    cloud-masking can be achieved through post-processing, the presence
    of clouds has the potential to obfuscate the phenomena of interest.
    Combined, these three disadvantages compound, resulting in much
    sparser data availability for Landsat imagery in comparison to
    Sentinel-1.</p>
    <p>Furthermore, while indices for surface water monitoring utilizing
    Landsat spectral bands, such as the Normalized Difference Water
    Index (NDWI), are widely used, they are imprecise classifiers on
    their own. NDWI in particular, is suspectable to misclassifying
    shadows as water. NDWI is defined as the difference between the
    green and near-infrared (NIR) bands divided by the sum of the green
    and NIR bands (for Landsat 8/9, bands 3 and 5 respectively;
    <xref alt="Equation 1" rid="eq-NDWI">Equation 1</xref>).</p>
    <p><styled-content id="eq-NDWI"><disp-formula><alternatives>
    <tex-math><![CDATA[
    NDWI = \frac{Green - NIR}{Green + NIR}
     \qquad(1)]]></tex-math>
    <mml:math display="block" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mspace width="2.0em"></mml:mspace><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true" form="prefix">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="true" form="postfix">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula></styled-content></p>
    <p>Despite these disadvantages, it may still be possible to
    characterize and quantify ephemeral water bodies using this
    dataset.</p>
    <p>Fortunately, Landsat data is freely available, easily accessible
    through GEE, and Landsat Collection 2 datasets include
    post-processing data which is directly applicable to this method,
    including cloud and cloud shadow masks, as well as a pre-calculated
    water mask (which appears to be largely coincident with NDWI &gt;
    0). However, this water mask is over inclusive, and not suitable for
    use as is.</p>
    <p>A large number of features identified as water in the provided
    Landsat water mask layer appeared to correspond to the northward
    aspect of terrain features. Therefore, to refine the provided layer
    by reducing the false positives resulting from natural terrain
    shadows I created a hillshade (or hill shadow) layer in GEE from a
    high resolution (10 m) USGS digital elevation model (DEM). For each
    image in the Landsat collection, sun angle and azimuth were obtained
    from the image metadata and passed to the hillshadow function to
    create a custom terrain shadow mask. The provided Landsat water mask
    was compared against the custom terrain shadow mask, and any
    purported water which overlapped a terrain shadow was removed.</p>
    <p>Upon evaluation, this method worked fairly well, but still left
    lots of small crescent shaped remnants of the Landsat water mask
    resulting from the mis-matched resolution of the imagery and the
    DEM. Therefore the hillshade was dilated using a local minimum
    function with a 150 m (5 pixel) square neighborhood. This
    effectively removed most of the remaining stippling and partial
    terrain shadows, however it also partially clipped some known water
    features, for example along the southern shore of Lake Mead.
    Although the accuracy has not been formally tested, visual analysis
    appears to confirm that the removal of false positives (terrain
    shadows) substantially outweighs the loss of true positives (masked
    water bodies).</p>
    <boxed-text>
    <p><bold>Note</bold></p>
    <p>This hillshadow dilation method was the first idea, and works
    reasonably well, with some losses of correctly identified water
    mask, particularly adjacent to steep terrain.</p>
    <p>An alternate strategy to reduce stippling and partial terrain
    shadows would be to identify and remove small features using a
    connected pixel count, as in the
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://travisz09.github.io/ATUR-RF-Flood-Map">Random
    Forest Flood Map</ext-link>.</p>
    </boxed-text>
    <p>This method appears to be working reasonably well, as it is
    consistently identifying know bodies of water such as Lake Mead,
    even appearing to capture fluctuating water levels in the lake’s
    headwaters, while limiting the number of false positives from
    terrain shadows
    (<xref alt="Figure 4" rid="fig-LakeMead_LS">Figure 4</xref>).
    However, it still requires on the ground validation with a known
    ephemeral water body. Additionally, there still remain some number
    of false positives associated with large building shadows (buildings
    are not included in DEMs), such as in Las Vegas, and a number of
    unmasked cloud shadows
    (<xref alt="Figure 5" rid="fig-clouds">Figure 5</xref>).</p>
    <fig id="fig-LakeMead_LS">
      <caption><p>Figure 4: Time series analysis of 22 Landsat images of
      Lake Mead and Hualapai Playa in 2020 with potential water sources
      mapped in blue. The more frequently a pixel was identified as
      water, the more saturated the color.</p></caption>
      <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="images/LakeMead_LS.png" />
    </fig>
    <fig id="fig-clouds">
      <caption><p>Figure 5: Google Earth Engine screen captures. A cloud
      moving over Hualapai Playa on 11/26/2020 cast a shadow which is
      only partially captured by the cloud mask (right; black), and is
      subsequently misclassified as water by the algorithm (right;
      blue).</p></caption>
      <table-wrap>
        <table>
          <colgroup>
            <col width="50%" />
            <col width="50%" />
          </colgroup>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="center"><p specific-use="wrapper">
                <boxed-text>
                  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="images/Clouds1.jpg" />
                </boxed-text>
              </p></td>
              <td align="center"><p specific-use="wrapper">
                <boxed-text>
                  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="images/Clouds2.jpg" />
                </boxed-text>
              </p></td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </table-wrap>
    </fig>
    <p>Despite its limitations compared to SAR data, this Landsat method
    has shown enormous potential. Further development of this method is
    warranted, and methodological improvements are likely. However, to
    fully validate this method <bold>we desperately need to find Landsat
    images of a known ephemeral water body when flooded</bold>. This
    need for a known test case to validate the method is made more
    challenging by the long revisit time of the Landsat satellites, as
    well as the need for clear (cloud free) conditions. <bold>Any
    available historical records of known flood events on Hualapai
    Playa, or other large playas in the state would be enormously
    helpful!</bold></p>
  </sec>
</sec>
<sec id="further-recommendations">
  <title>3 Further Recommendations</title>
</sec>
<sec id="conclusion">
  <title>4 Conclusion</title>
</sec>
</body>

<back>
<ref-list>
  <title>References</title>
  <ref id="ref-Clifford_Crawford">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>Clifford S.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Chapter 17 - the invertebrate community of ephemeral waters</article-title>
      <source>Biology of desert invertebrates</source>
      <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>
      <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      <year iso-8601-date="1981">1981</year>
      <isbn>978-3-642-85796-6</isbn>
      <fpage>234</fpage>
      <lpage>247</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Whitford_Duval_2020">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Whitford</surname><given-names>Walter G.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Duval</surname><given-names>Benjamin D.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Chapter 8 - consumers and their effects</article-title>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Whitford</surname><given-names>Walter G.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Duval</surname><given-names>Benjamin D.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2020-01">2020</year><month>01</month>
      <isbn>978-0-12-815055-9</isbn>
      <uri>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/B9780128150559000084</uri>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-815055-9.00008-4</pub-id>
      <fpage>203</fpage>
      <lpage>263</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Tran_Menenti_Jia_2022">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>Khuong H.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Menenti</surname><given-names>Massimo</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>Li</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Surface water mapping and flood monitoring in the mekong delta using sentinel-1 SAR time series and otsu threshold</article-title>
      <source>Remote Sensing</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year>
      <volume>14</volume>
      <issue>22</issue>
      <issn>2072-4292</issn>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/rs14225721</pub-id>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-GEE_A2.3">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Markert</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Donchyts</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Haag</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Chapter A2.3 surface water mapping</article-title>
      <source>Cloud-based remote sensing with google earth engine: Fundamentals and applications</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Cardille</surname><given-names>Jeffrey A.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Clinton</surname><given-names>Nick</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Crowley</surname><given-names>Morgan A</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Saah</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <publisher-name>Springer Cham</publisher-name>
      <year iso-8601-date="2023-05">2023</year><month>05</month>
      <edition>1</edition>
      <isbn>978-3-031-26587-7</isbn>
      <uri>https://docs.google.com/document/d/12cwzbNXtBQnm5switfL1vlv1stnp5D5gXcQeZMP_iJI/edit?tab=t.0#heading=h.2gd4k88k0hkr</uri>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-otsu1975threshold">
    <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Otsu</surname><given-names>Nobuyuki</given-names></name>
        <etal/>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>A threshold selection method from gray-level histograms</article-title>
      <source>Automatica</source>
      <year iso-8601-date="1975">1975</year>
      <volume>11</volume>
      <issue>285-296</issue>
      <fpage>23</fpage>
      <lpage>27</lpage>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
  <ref id="ref-Franz_Meyer_2019">
    <element-citation publication-type="chapter">
      <person-group person-group-type="author">
        <name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>Franz</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <article-title>Chapter 2 - spaceborne synthetic aperture radar: Principles, data access, and basic processing techniques</article-title>
      <source>The SAR handbook: Comprehensive methodologies for forest monitoring and biomass estimation</source>
      <person-group person-group-type="editor">
        <name><surname>Flores-Anderson</surname><given-names>Africa</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Herndon</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Thapa</surname><given-names>Rajesh</given-names></name>
        <name><surname>Cherrington</surname><given-names>Emil</given-names></name>
      </person-group>
      <year iso-8601-date="2019-04">2019</year><month>04</month>
      <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.25966/nr2c-s697</pub-id>
    </element-citation>
  </ref>
</ref-list>
</back>



</article>